<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Mike Lady's Personal Site</title>
    <description>Grappling with humans and code. Striving to be the hero of my own story and sharing what I learn along the way.
</description>
    <link>https://michaellady.github.io//</link>
    <atom:link href="https://michaellady.github.io//feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Tue, 04 May 2021 10:43:48 -0700</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 04 May 2021 10:43:48 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v4.2.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>On Writing in the Morning</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Only about a week back did I decide to try to write every morning. The words flow easier right when I get up. It’s a nice little ritual where I go and make my coffee and sit down at the counter with my laptop and start getting my ideas out. It’s a nice, cozy way to mentally “warm up” for the day, kind of like when we all show up at 6am jiu-jitsu class and shoot the shit for 15-20 mins before any jiu-jitsu happens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s also this weird desire that I’ve had over the last couple of years to put more content out. I’ve been mostly quiet on social media before then, occasionally posting when something important happens. I basically post every day now. I think it comes from a desire to share and pass on my ideas, and a bit of social validation. I think my ideas are good. Hell, they’ve gotten me this far so they must be, but it helps to confirm that I’m not crazy, and that people get value from the content I post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s this idea from Richard Dawkins of “memes” (before they were internet jokes), where ideas have a kind of “DNA” and their own process of natural selection. Adaptive ideas are passed on to the next generation, and maladaptive ones are discarded. The first draft of the previous sentence had “good” and “bad”, but then I remembered my biology classes. In that biologically-driven way, I want to put more of my ideas out into the world, to pass on the knowledge to others, and leave my mark in society as a force for “good”. Given the previous discussion on adaptive vs. maladaptive, I want to help the human race continue with adaptive ideas that enable people to live their best, fulfilled lives. That’s the ultimate &lt;a href=&quot;/dev/2017/11/21/On-Being-A-Support-Hero.html&quot;&gt;“force multiplier”&lt;/a&gt; that I can be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Largely without religion, this generation and upcoming ones have to create their own purpose in the world. I found mine through physical and mental grappling, and that was over the course of iterating and meandering through a lot of different things. I didn’t get it right the first try, or the second, or even the fourth. Most people don’t even want to start to try to move in a direction for fear of being wrong, and just accept whatever direction they are already going in. Even if you change and go in the wrong direction, you’ll at least know &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; that was the wrong direction, and you will be able to course-correct for the next change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the phrases that annoyed me most when I was graduating college and had a job offer in hand already was that I was “set”. I was just beginning! What was “set”??? Things were far from “set”, and still are, and won’t be until I’m in the ground.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s it. That’s the process. Life is a process. There isn’t an “stopping point”, or “end” to it while you’re living. If it isn’t changing, you’re dead. Things will always change, and you have to decide how to change (or not) along with them.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 15 Apr 2020 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://michaellady.github.io//dev/2020/04/15/On-Writing-in-the-Morning.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://michaellady.github.io//dev/2020/04/15/On-Writing-in-the-Morning.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>dev</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Quarantine Hyperbolic Time Chamber</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Jiu-jitsu and life in general is going to have an interesting “reset” after this quarantine. There’s going to be people who took advantage of the time they were given, and those who didn’t. I’m treating every day like an opportunity to get an edge on my opponents. About one month in, I’m approximately the same weight, 230 lbs, but there is a definite difference in my strength levels and I’m looking a little leaner, indicating some muscle gain and fat loss. This is honestly pretty good for a body recomposition goal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/weight_quarantine_m1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Weight over first month of quarantine&quot; title=&quot;Weight over first month of quarantine&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best advice I’ve heard (I think it was from Layne Norton when he was on Joe Rogan Experience) is that you want to lose weight as slow as possible. The context in which he said that was that fighters cut incredible amounts of weight in very short periods of time. He says that the body (via the metabolism?) remembers these extreme cases of starvation and successive weight cuts get harder and harder. The body wants to hold on to as much weight as possible since it knows that starvation is a threat that it had to survive before. His advice was essentially to trick your body into accepting an ever so slightly lower calorie norm. Get your body used to a small reduction in total energy over a longer period of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I haven’t been tracking calories or macros closely at this time, although after looking at the weight graph, seeing a 1 lb increase over 30 days makes me want to tighten things up a little bit. I do make sure I’m getting enough protein. That has been a lacking feature of my diet over the years. I enjoy the hell out of carbs. I love bread and sugar in all of its various forms. I have two ways that I have basically “bought insurance” for myself to raise my baseline of protein over time: meal prep and pre-packaged protein shakes. These two options are definitely more expensive than the alternatives of cooking for myself and powdered protein.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem is with the cheaper options is that I never did them. I’m a lazy software developer; it is a feature, not a bug of my profession. I hate the process of cooking and having to clean dishes afterwards. Pretty much the same kind of reasoning follows for having to “prepare” the protein shake, gulp it down as fast as possible, and then having to clean the shaker cup afterwards. Do these sound like minor, child-like complaints? Absolutely. Am I spending more money than others for similar results? Yes. Have I been stronger than ever due to better adherence as a result? 100%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m willing to invest in my sports performance and ultimately my health now because I have a limited time window to compete in jiu-jitsu. Also the convenient side effect of being healthy now means fewer medical expenses later on in life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, and by the way, I’m also holding down a demanding full-time job as a software developer. There are certain times where work interferes with my training schedule, but that does not happen often. Having a full time job, health insurance, and disposable income enables this whole sport to happen for me: gym dues, tournament entry fees, travel, etc. I wouldn’t say at all that it really ever gets in the way. I can always work around it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why did I just sketch out the different aspects of my life like this? I’m setting up parameters for my personal Quarantine Hyperbolic Time Chamber&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;quarantine-hyperbolic-time-chamber&quot;&gt;Quarantine Hyperbolic Time Chamber&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you were a kid growing up in the early 2000s, at some point, you watched Dragon Ball Z on Cartoon Network Toonami after school. I have fond memories of coming home from school on Friday afternoons, and sitting on the floor eating Pizza Hut pizza while watching Toonami with my brother.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dragon Ball Z is a show about the hero’s journey, cycled over and over again. There’s always another big bad guy looming in the shadows when one is defeated. The stakes are raised constantly. In order for the heroes to keep up with the bigger, badder antagonists, the show introduces the Hyperbolic Time Chamber. The Hyperbolic Time Chamber has a special property where 1 year in the chamber is equivalent to 1 day in the real world. Therefore, it is place where heroes go to get massive amounts of training done in a short period of “real time”. The chamber acted almost like a “fight camp” for protagonists Dragon Ball Z before they go and fight the next bad guy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was also an isolating factor to the chamber; only two characters could enter at a time. The characters would experience an entire year of time with each other, and each other only. I don’t remember any character arc details at this point, but I’m sure they were there. This is also very similar to quarantine because you get to know whoever you’re quarantined with very well in that short period of time since they are the only people there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have an opportunity right now during this quarantine to step in our own Hyperbolic Time Chamber, because on the other side of this, we’re going to get back to the “real world” and we’ll have to pick up where we left off with whatever next “big bad guy” we have to fight in our lives. What specifically do you want to accomplish?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My days mostly look like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;5:30am - 7:00am Wake up / write&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;7:00am - 8:30am Strength and Conditioning&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;8:30am - 9:00am Shower and breakfast&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;9:00am - 12:00pm Work&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;12:00pm - 1:00pm Have lunch with my girlfriend&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1:00pm - 5:30pm Work&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;5:30pm - 6:00pm Swing some clubbells around&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;6:00pm - 10:00pm Dinner and spend time with my girlfriend&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;10:00pm - 5:30am Sleep&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each block of time is building an aspect of my life that I want to be prepared for after the quarantine. I get up and write first thing in the morning because it gives me mental clarity and direction for what I’m working towards: my “why”. Next I make good on the “why” I contemplated in a very tangible, physical way by training my body. After training hard, I refuel by eating a good breakfast and I’m ready to take on the challenges at work. I get a midday respite from solving challenges at work by spending time with my girlfriend, which refuels me for the remainder of the workday. I shake out any feelings of tension left over from work by practicing something I’m fairly new at in swinging clubbells. Then I relax into the evening with my girlfriend, recharging me for the next day of hard work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you noticed there’s a bit of a yin and yang to this. There’s push and pull; I exert energy, then I recover. I feel very balanced and that I can sustain this for as long as the quarantine lasts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What does your Quarantine Hyperbolic Time Chamber look like? Let me know if I can help.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 14 Apr 2020 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://michaellady.github.io//dev/2020/04/14/The-Quarantine-Hyperbolic-Time-Chamber.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://michaellady.github.io//dev/2020/04/14/The-Quarantine-Hyperbolic-Time-Chamber.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>dev</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Technique AND Strength</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This morning was the first time during the quarantine where I didn’t get up and work out first thing. I was up late doing work, and had to do finish up some things for work Friday morning. I was able to make it up later at lunch time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today’s anomaly made me realize that I have been on a tear with weight lifting during the quarantine, to give myself a pat on the back. I haven’t trained jiu-jitsu in weeks, and probably won’t be able to for at least another month. That leaves plenty of time for me to continue to develop strength, durability, and probably most importantly, conditioning that I have been sorely neglecting. It’s interesting, pretty much for the last year and a half or so, I bought into the adage “technique over strength”, since I was so focused on getting my purple belt. To be fair, it has served me well. Like I explained in a &lt;a href=&quot;/grappling/2020/04/07/Quarantined-Thoughts-About-Jiu-Jitsu.html&quot;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt;, the difference between me at white belt and purple belt is not physicality, but my ability to apply effective technique. Unfortunately, this adage has given me wiggle room to not train my strength. Maybe it’s time for me to follow a new adage, “technique AND strength”, with a nerdy embedded meaning: logical AND.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Long, totally overthinking it post ahead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TL;DR: maybe you should simultaneously get better at jiu-jitsu and take care of and improve the vehicle you do jiu-jitsu with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;technique-and-strength&quot;&gt;Technique AND Strength&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Think of all of your favorite competitive grapplers, and what do they look like? With exceptions like Marcelo Garcia, they’re likely all jacked, or at least, not out of shape. That is because at the highest black belt level, they are relatively close in technique, or at least are equally capable of defending submissions and can strategize within the bounds of whatever ruleset they are competing in. There is some threshold of technique that you have to have to be competitive. Once you cross that threshold, strength comes into play. That is the meaning of the logical AND. When computers evaluate an AND condition, they evaluate the left hand term (like a math equation) first, so in this case, that is “technique”. If that term is “true”, then it evaluates the right hand term, in this case, “strength”. If the left hand term does NOT evaluate to true, then it doesn’t even try to evaluate the rest of the condition, since AND requires both terms to be true to continue. An example of this is white belt Mike vs. purple belt Mike. I lifted way more weights at white belt, and I was probably in better shape conditioning-wise as well, but I would have a very small chance of beating purple belt Mike in any kind of ruleset. The technique term encapsulates many different aspects of jiu-jitsu, so let’s try to unpack that term.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-technique-term&quot;&gt;The “Technique” Term&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Technique can mean many things to many different people, and I think they’re all probably correct to varying degrees. The way I’ll define it here is not any more or less valid than other perspectives. It is just how I make sense of it in my own head.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll define technique as “the right movement at the right time”. I noticed this most when I roll with higher belts. Black belts don’t beat me because they can out-lift me (I’m sure many do anyways), but instead, they beat me because they use the right move for slicing through my guard (or anything else) like butter at the right time. It is educational and ego-destroying to have the same move done to me over and over and I am practically helpless to stop it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is almost like playing &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/rB9Nmx5Patc?t=93&quot;&gt;Dance Dance Revolution (DDR)&lt;/a&gt; and timing your steps on the arrow pads to get points. At some point you might mess up your timing, and give the other player the lead. If that player is good enough, they can maintain and build that lead by not messing up themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have also heard and tend to agree that jiu-jitsu is sort of like ping pong or tennis, sometimes you just need to return the ball to stay in the game, and you won’t have an opportunity to hit a powerful attacking shot every time the ball is in your court. The idea however, is to put yourself into that attacking position over time. Another aspect of ping pong / tennis that I’ll highlight here is that there’s a limited window of opportunity to decide and act. If you miss it, you have lost by default. You can see the other player’s movement of how they’re going to play the ball, you see the ball coming across the net, and then there’s the moment of truth where you have to decide what movement you’re going to use the moment the ball strikes your side of the court. You can’t hesitate because you only have the amount of time the ball is in the air to act before it bounces again and the point is scored for your opponent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These two analogies, DDR and tennis, make up my definition of “timing”. Even if I was a much much stronger individual with the same level of technique, the black belts I roll with would still have answers for each of the physical “problems” I posed. This is my analogy for defining “movement”: this time we’ll use rock climbing and puzzles in general. In rock climbing at a gym, when you look at the wall, you see dozens of multicolored funky shaped grips. They call each path of the same colored hand and foot grips a “problem”. Each problem has a level of difficulty and you can “decode” what movements the route-planners intended you to take to “solve” the problem. Of course, you can choose to not do those suggested encoded movements, either by naïveté because you’re so new you don’t understand them or because you’re that good and you desire a challenge. Same thing with jiu-jitsu. Each person presents one or more problems to solve while they’re trying to solve your problem(s). There are certain movements that are more correct in certain situations than others, but if you’re that good, you can YOLO it (strategically, of course) and see what happens. To further extend the rock climbing analogy, certain movements take a certain level of physical attributes to perform. You need to be dexterous enough to place your foot here, or have enough balance to maintain your footing there, or have enough strength to pull yourself up or hold on to an awkward grip.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“But Mike!”, you might say, “You said the word ‘strength’! Doesn’t that defeat your / other’s point about strength being separate from technique?” Yes, I said the word “strength”, but let me define it in this context: it is the bare minimum amount of effort expended to achieve a certain goal. You could also say that good movement is “efficient” in this way. I would say if you do not have the level of strength (or any other physical attribute) to perform a movement, and go and do exercises to improve your strength (or any other physical attribute) for that movement, you are really working on your technique, not your “strength”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Strength is what you see when two heavyweight whitebelts spaz on each other for 5 minutes in a round and then they are both exhausted afterwards. They then claim they need to work on their “cardio”. What they need is more technique. Embedded in that is more efficient movement. Efficient movement requires as little energy as possible to accomplish the goal. I am barely breathing hard when I get done with rolls with most lower belts, since I have enough of a technique advantage to be efficient in my energy management and I am consciously trying to roll anywhere from 50-70% energy expenditure. I know when I need to push the pedal to the metal and when to let off the gas. This is in comparison to white belts who have very little technique and try to make up for it in energy and using strength when they roll. This is also the same comparison to me when I roll with my belt level and higher. At my same belt level, our technique is even, so often the deciding factors are strength and conditioning. Or with higher belts, I don’t have as much technique as them, so when I start to get behind in the position game, I try to use strength to make up for it. In both cases, I end up very gassed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-strength-term&quot;&gt;The “Strength” Term&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since I borrowed some portion of “Strength” in the “Technique” section (but really broadened it to “physical attributes”), I’ll define this section as, “the ability to turn technique &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/KOO5S4vxi0o&quot;&gt;up to 11&lt;/a&gt;”. Use of strength is almost by definition “inefficient”. When you drive a car faster than about 60 mph on the freeway, you are making a tradeoff for using more gas in order to save time to get to where you are going. This is the same in competition energy management. Nobody competitive at your belt level is going to let you walk through their guard, roll over, and tap out for you. Competition is a struggle. You have a limited amount of time (in most rulesets) to prove which one of you is more dominant, and it is an all out race to the finish line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the part of the sport where you have to become a savage. There is a primal reward system in our brains for fighting, and this sport is the closest we can get to it on a consistent basis without getting seriously injured. Every time you and your partner slap-bump and roll, it is a simulated fight to the death. In competition, the stakes are that much higher. How do you want to prepare for that? Do you want to go into a competition, a simulated do-or-die situation, as a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.graciepoway.com/history-of-gracie-jiu-jitsu&quot;&gt;“frail Helio”&lt;/a&gt;, or as a dynamic, robust, durable, tank of a man? See any current top jiu-jitsu competitor as an example. You want to stack as many advantages in your favor as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s the simple full-body template that I’m following every day for adding strength and durability during the quarantine:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;warmup&quot;&gt;Warmup&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Light bands and kettlebell halos for shoulders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Planks up front because they suck and if I don’t do them here, I won’t do them otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;superset-1-3---5-sets&quot;&gt;Superset 1, 3 - 5 sets&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Upper body push (push ups or dips or overhead press)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Upper body pull (rows or pull ups or chin ups)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;superset-2-3---5-sets&quot;&gt;Superset 2, 3 - 5 sets&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lower body push (a lunge variant or squat or other quad-dominant movement)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lower body pull (nordic hamstring curls or any other hamstring-dominant movement)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conditioning&quot;&gt;Conditioning&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kettlebell swings x 100 (broken up into whatever sets that you can perform with good technique: 10 x 10 reps, 5 x 20 reps, 4 x 25 reps, etc)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By not going crazy on volume every day and alternating movements, I’m not sore, and I’m able to keep myself moving every day. I want to continue this program out of the quarantine in order to work on my Strength while able to still train hard at jiu-jitsu to work on my Technique.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;other-perspectives&quot;&gt;Other perspectives?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m a mere purple belt. I am not a world champion or anywhere close to it. These opinions are my own and just the perspective of how I see the world. Please let me know if there’s another perspective that I may be missing or if I’m totally wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 10 Apr 2020 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://michaellady.github.io//grappling/2020/04/10/Technique-and-Strength.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://michaellady.github.io//grappling/2020/04/10/Technique-and-Strength.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>grappling</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Great Weight Shortage of 2020</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;As all “non-essential” businesses closed around the country mid-March 2020, there were many unanticipated knock-on effects. The effects that hit most close to home was: 1. the jiu-jitsu gyms I train at closing, and one closing a location permanently, and 2. the mainstream weight lifting gyms closed as well. This left many out in the cold without a place to exercise or equipment to train with. I was fortunate enough to already have a small home gym already started with dumbbells, kettlebells, and a pull up bar. As I started having to rely on my home gym as my sole source of exercise, I looked into purchasing more equipment for it. I was looking for some mid-weight dumbbells, 55 - 70 lbs. What I found was a volatile retail marketplace and secondary market not unlike the stock market at the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of the major retailers were sold out of weights of all varieties: dumbbells, kettlebells, barbell plates, etc. Then, something interesting happened. On various secondary market sites like Facebook Marketplace or OfferUp, the prices of weights went through the roof. Generally with selling used consumer-grade weights, they tend to hold their value anywhere from $0.50 per pound of weight on the very low end for some rusty-ass weights to $2 per pound of weight for nice rubberized weights, with $1 per pound being a very fair price.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I saw befuddled me, but made sense the more I thought about it. Rusty-ass weights were now being listed for $2 per pound, and newer, nicer rubberized weights were listed up to $3 per pound. This shows markets in action. With demand very suddenly outstripping supply, sellers were able to ask for higher-than-retail prices since retail was suddenly a non-factor. From this starting point, there are a couple of lines of reasoning that flow from it for why the price of weights went up so dramatically right around end of March, beginning of April.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;rent-due-on-april-1st&quot;&gt;Rent due on April 1st.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, with the shutdown of “non-essential” businesses mid-March, those shutdown businesses couldn’t pay their employees, so those people who suddenly didn’t have a job still had to make rent. Weights aren’t necessary for survival, and normally have a very active secondary market, so they are naturally a good candidate for selling to make ends meet. What I think drove prices higher in this instance is that the people who were selling weights were looking to meet an elevated total sales target to match or at least put a sizable dent in their total expenses that their job would normally cover. That high of a sales target is something generally individuals wouldn’t be able to do unless they’re buying and selling a large volume of weights as a part-time to full-time business. So in order to try to hit that fairly lofty sales target for the limited inventory that they have, they had to price their weights accordingly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sellers-marking-items-as-sold-and-then-re-listing-them&quot;&gt;Sellers marking items as “sold”, and then re-listing them.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another phenomenon I noticed when following the weight market was that sellers, after posting an entirely too high of a price their weights and they don’t sell after a few days, mark their listing as “SOLD”, and then repost those same weights with either the same or different picture for a little bit lower price. This definitely had an influence on other sellers when determining the market value of weights that they themselves would want to sell. Other sellers would see some rusty-ass weights being marked as “SOLD” for $2 per pound, then they feel like they could get the same or even more for what they wanted to sell. This also contributed to the confidence in sellers holding their prices firmly higher than retail value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;price-tolerant-buyers&quot;&gt;Price tolerant buyers.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everyone who wished to continue to train with significant weight while gyms were shut down were suddenly in the market for weights that they can lift at home. This sudden uptick in the demand for weights drove buyers first to retail sites, which were quickly sold out, and then to secondary markets. The type of people who were health-conscious and dedicated to consistently training at a gym were willing to pay more than retail price for a home weight set to continue to at least maintain their hard-earned gains that they made pre-quarantine. The health-conscious type of person who was willing to pay above retail price for a home set of weights probably also had more disposable income to spare and were probably relatively unaffected by the sudden shutdown of “non-essential” businesses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;any-other-interesting-effects&quot;&gt;Any other interesting effects?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, I just thought this was an interesting example of ECON101 at play in a space that I cared about, since I was in the market for weights at the time. Let me know of any other interesting examples (besides toilet-paper-as-currency memes) where the quarantine made something interesting happen in a space that you care about.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 09 Apr 2020 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://michaellady.github.io//dev/2020/04/09/The-Great-Weight-Shortage-of-2020.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://michaellady.github.io//dev/2020/04/09/The-Great-Weight-Shortage-of-2020.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>dev</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Quarantined Thoughts About Jiu-Jitsu</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Sitting outside on my deck… being quarantined doesn’t seem so bad. The sun is shining. the sky is blue, it’s warm outside, but it’s a bit breezy. It doesn’t seem like the world has ground to a virtual halt since it’s such a beautiful day outside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m holding it together. I’m grateful that I’m still employed. I’m exercising every day, roughly structuring parts of my workouts like: upper body push, upper body pull, lower body quad dominant, lower body hamstring dominant, then conditioning with kettlebell swings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel stronger already, but there’s a monotony to only getting better at the “physical attributes” of my body, which is only one part of my overall goal of being the best grappler I can be. There’s also the monotony of having to watch technique videos, but no real way to apply the techniques learned right away. You can’t simply “mentally train” your way to great jiu-jitsu, you have to be able to apply it at the right time on an opponent who is trying to do the same thing to you. Maybe that’s why it feels incomplete. The joy of rolling (sparring) is the intersection between these two elements: the physical and the mental.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It would behoove me to prepare more of the mental side… I’ve been slacking. It really is one half of the game. The difference between me at purple belt and me at white belt are not physical attributes. The difference is the application of the techniques I have learned over time. I would probably do to white belt Mike that I felt the receiving end of when I first started. For 6 months, I walked into triangles and armbars since I pressured in so much. It was a habit from wrestling that died hard. Some white belt competition videos from 7 years ago came up in my “Facebook memories” feed, and I can now confirm this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A happy medium for me seems to be watching my competition footage. It is part analyzing technique, and it is also part narcissism because it is me in the video that is actually trying to perform the technique. There’s something to trying to work out what I remember experiencing at the time, as well as trying to see other opportunities or details that I may have missed in the heat of the match. Watching film of my matches is also relevant because the guy in the film plays the exact same game that I do! I watched a number of matches that I lost over the last year and found mistakes in each one of those matches (obviously). I never felt strictly outclassed technique-wise by people my belt rank; I have always been competitive in each of my matches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s interesting that in training, I feel more of a technical challenge than in competition. In training, you’re mixed in with a variety of belt ranks. When I was a white belt, anybody blue and above could destroy me. Now, almost 8 years later, I compete and do well at purple belt, I give brown belts a good roll but they still have a step ahead on me, and Black belts can still do whatever they want to me. That’s the humbling part. I’ve come this far, but I still have so far to go. I think that’s the growth curve of jiu-jitsu and why it’s so hard: it is exponential growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each belt promotion may represent “25%” of your path to black belt (white to blue, blue to purple, purple to brown, brown to black), but the technical development between each promotion is much more than the previous one. You learn how to learn better and you grow your established game over time. As an upper belt, it is easier to add on a technique to your game if you already know the 6-10 techniques that lead up to it. It’s just one step off your beaten path. At white belt, you’re trying to grasp at disjoint techniques that don’t seem to have anything to do with each other, and for the technique you don’t know, you fill in with energy and physical attributes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which brings me back to physical attributes. In order to apply technique effectively, you need a baseline of physical attributes. Your body must be able to do certain things in order to perform the techniques correctly. This baseline raises higher and higher as you progress up the belt ranks, and especially when you’re a competitor, you never &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt; to be weaker than your opponent, it just sometimes works out that way. As the famous powerlifter Mark Bell says, “strength is never a weakness”. So in this way, the quarantine is forcing me to raise my baseline of physical attributes, which have probably been lacking since I’ve been focusing so much on technique and getting to purple belt. The physical attributes and more importantly, habits that I develop during this time will allow me to chart a course for the physical demands that are required of me for the next belt and level of competition.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 07 Apr 2020 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://michaellady.github.io//grappling/2020/04/07/Quarantined-Thoughts-About-Jiu-Jitsu.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://michaellady.github.io//grappling/2020/04/07/Quarantined-Thoughts-About-Jiu-Jitsu.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>grappling</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Post Tournament Analysis: Grappling Industries 1/19/19</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;TL;DR: I won 4 matches against my only opponent. I respect the hell out of anyone who comes and competes in a sportsmanlike way, and my opponent was a great example of that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Going into this competition, it was a weird feeling. It was a round-robin tournament format, so if you had enough people in your division, you could face a variety of opponents and gain a lot of good experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But not in the Adult Blue Belt 230lbs division. What I had to prepare for was a bit different than what was advertised. After the sign up deadline passed, and there were for certain no more competitors listed in my division, there was a potential for a total of 6 hard-fought matches with the same dude over the course of the day. My training partners called this scenario “an actual war, with multiple battles”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thinking over the “actual war” scenario, the prospect of facing the same guy potentially that many times seemed to be more nerve-wracking than having to face 3 different people twice, or 6 people once!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe because I let the thought of “what if I lose badly to this guy? Multiple times?? In front of all of my friends and teammates?!?” marinade in my head a bit too long. I let this worse-case scenario play out and take a foothold in my head.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The opposite scenario also played out in my head, but to a much smaller degree. Even with the most optimal scenario (winning by submission for every match), I discounted it as being “not a big deal”, since I’m only beating one guy. After having that scenario basically play out (3 subs, 1 win by points, a still very decisive positive outcome), I’m still sitting in the camp of, “eh, it’s a local tournament, not a big deal. It’s not Worlds”, which I think is healthy given that I plan on competing many more times this year. But let me contrast the absolute best case scenario with the worse case scenario for a second.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought it was going to be a fairly negative, demotivating thing if I got beat bad in front of my friends and teammates… but a “meh” on the most positive, best case upside? Isn’t that weird? The explanation I’ve heard about this phenomenon is that, evolutionarily, we are hard wired to focus on the potential negative outcomes of any set of actions more than the potential positive ones. This tendency has allowed us, as a species, to survive this long under the thumb of scarcity; carefully planning our every move to maximize the odds of us living a long(er) life, thereby increasing our changes of procreation. But this isn’t the optimal mindset for a world where there’s now too many readily-available calories (in the United States, at least, where those who are reading are most likely from and where my perspective has formed). Life has gotten very comfortable survival-wise for most people in the US and many can sit through life without having to endure any hard physical challenges if they so choose to. I digress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actual technical tournament recap time!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I need to improve my takedown game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There, I said it. Most jiu-jitsu guys are happy to pull guard to their heart’s content, but not me. The wrestler in me is too proud. I want to fight for the advantage that is being top.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel like I’ve come full circle. I started out in jiu-jitsu only knowing wrestling, then learning how to apply my wrestling to the jiu-jitsu top game, then only developing my guard game until well after earning my blue belt. I have finally gotten to the point where I am fairly confident in my ability to at least retain guard and get to my main sweeps, at which point I can then leverage my much stronger top game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I now need to circle back to, (you guessed it, you wrestler reading this) circling. Inducing movement to set up takedowns. Kuzushi. Whatever you want to call it. I need more of it. The first part of all of the matches I had at Grappling Industries could be, in fact, mistaken for two rhinos butting heads. Granted, my opponent made me move a bit more after he started using my own favorite upper body clinches against me (Russian two on one, armdrags), but not by much. I did have a bit of “ring rust” to knock off before I felt comfortable with just being in the moment and letting my training take over.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My most successful takedowns were off of snap downs, which wasn’t super surprising to me, since I have a deep appreciation for how safe they are to execute (and fail at) compared to how effective they can be when they do work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other major hole in my game: taking the back from the turtle position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Granted, I finished my opponent with 3 rear strangles (1 lapel, two RNCs), but I did “fall off” of the back a couple of times in the process. This was because he wasn’t properly broken down before I attacked the back, which was my fault. I was able to snake one leg in while he was still very based up. After reviewing the film, shot by the thoughtful Doug Mccaslin (I didn’t ask him to film, but I’m glad he did!), I could have totally used “the truck” as an alternative method to breaking my opponent down to attack submissions like the calf slicer or to just take the back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alright, one thing I was proud of: the effectiveness of my deep half guard sweep.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had to throw it twice when I fell off of my opponent’s back, and it worked exactly as intended both times. The first time I did the typical “Homer Simpson” sweep. He tried to kimura my far arm, but I had my hand tucked underneath his leg. I came up on top, stapled the bottom leg and proceeded to mount and submit him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second time I threw the deep half, since he had seen it before in the previous match, he stepped around my head for a kneebar. This is another common reaction I have trained for as well. As soon as he stepped around, I grabbed his far leg at the hip and swept him back to the mat and came on top in a similar fashion to the first time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, I felt good and I didn’t get too banged up. That’s really all I can ask for after competing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m looking forward to posting future breakdowns of my matches. Stay tuned, and thank you for reading!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obligatory reminder to Share / Like / Subscribe&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 21 Jan 2019 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>https://michaellady.github.io//grappling/2019/01/21/Grappling-Industries-Post-Tournament-Analysis.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://michaellady.github.io//grappling/2019/01/21/Grappling-Industries-Post-Tournament-Analysis.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>grappling</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>About to Graduate? Get ready to Time Warp.</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;First off, I just want to say congratulations to you, future/current/former Cal Poly CSC/CPE/SE Student.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will get / are getting / have gotten one of the best values in college education, bar none. Cal Poly grads come out of gate with real hands-on project-based experience, debugging skills, and a good general understanding of what lies beneath the surface of the terminal / IDE. You also picked one of the best degrees to actually pay back your student loans. The people you attend classes with, work late into the night with, and socialize with are going to be some of the movers and shakers of your industry in the coming years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But you know all of that already.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What you don’t know is that after you graduate, you will enter a “Time Warp”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me explain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are even remotely interested in graduating on time, you probably have a 4 year course plan. Here was mine:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/4yearplan.png&quot;&gt; &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/4yearplan.png&quot; alt=&quot;alt text&quot; title=&quot;4 year plan in Google Sheets&quot; /&gt; &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was based on the 2009–2010 course catalog. I put it into google sheets so I could better manipulate which courses could fit where. Yes, I actually took ballet. I spent many HOURS procrastinating by planning quarters or years ahead in my college career. It was addictive. I was addicted to the feeling of “optimizing” and “planning ahead”, even while I had work to do that was due that week. That I could move these units here or there to better optimize my future chances of success, almost like playing Tetris.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I stopped.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I graduated the Spring of 2014 and never had to take another course for credit. No more curriculums. No more worrying about flowcharts. No more incremental units to optimize and fit into nicely timed blocks of 10 weeks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What did this mean? No more changing schedules and getting to learn something completely new every quarter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One quarter my schedule looked like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/schedule1.png&quot;&gt; &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/schedule1.png&quot; alt=&quot;alt text&quot; /&gt; &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the next one was like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/schedule2.png&quot;&gt; &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/schedule2.png&quot; alt=&quot;alt text&quot; /&gt; &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m sure many of you have a similar experiences with class schedules changing radically quarter to quarter. College schedules are nice in their own way: breaks in-between classes, classes starting later in the day, getting done with class early in the day, and even sometimes complete “days off” of class!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now contrast this with my current schedule:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/currentSchedule.png&quot;&gt; &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/currentSchedule.png&quot; alt=&quot;alt text&quot; /&gt; &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please note that I work remotely (maybe worthy of another post), so this doesn’t quite factor in commute time. In the Bay Area, your door-to-door commute time could be upwards of an hour or more just one way. A “good” commute is 30 minutes one way! Note that this “good” case is an hour a day in total, 5 days a week. This means if you are lucky, you are spending 10 full days out of a year in commute time! I’ve made lifestyle changes to minimize that time and when I have to, I use that time wisely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s an example of a schedule with an hour-long commute:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/hourCommute.png&quot;&gt; &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/hourCommute.png&quot; alt=&quot;alt text&quot; /&gt; &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the hardest things I had to get used to when entering the professional world was the feeling of being “at work” 8 hours a day. If you’ve had an internship or two, you’ll have had some sense of this. But even internship days are broken up by ping pong, lunches out, HR events, etc. As an intern, you likely aren’t tasked with any mission-critical functionality, so it is unlikely that you have to spend any late nights in the office under pressure to put out fires. The main purpose of an internship program is for you to succeed and give you a desire to come back and work at that company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you are hired on your first “full-time” job, things subtly change from when you were an intern. In the first three to six months, there’s a bit of a learning curve where you are expected to ask your senior Devs / PMs / Managers / etc lots of questions to get adjusted to the development environment, team culture, and generally “learning how to adult”. You may feel like an impostor, but that’s okay! It is part of the process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After that initial three to six month adjustment period, your only objectives after that are to make and effectively communicate significant progress on whatever you’re working on week-to-week, and meet deadlines as they come up. That’s it. Do those two-ish things and you’ll be a successful, gainfully-employed developer for the foreseeable future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is where the Time Warp happens: right when you become content, and settle into a routine. Your life is now chunked up into “product releases” instead of college “quarters”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The important differences between the two are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Your schedule doesn’t change much after every release&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There won’t be vast differences in what you’re working on. You won’t be working on Machine Learning instead of Networks, OS instead of Mobile Dev, etc. Instead, you’re going to be focusing in on further mastery of your role (Mobile, Front End, Back End, DevOps, etc).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe you think you can outsmart point 1 by taking a day or two or a week off after each release. Great, sounds like a step towards a healthy work-life balance! When you’re done with your PTO, it is “back on the treadmill” and on to working on the next release, further deepening the skills of your role à la point 2. This treadmill is how days bleed into weeks, weeks into months, and months into years. One day you’ll wake up and you’ll be 27-dreading-30 and you, dear reader, will also be writing your own alumni blog post :D&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what does this Time Warp mean? Let me be clear: I am by no means disparaging or saying anything negative about corporate life. I quite enjoy it and it has enabled me to do many of the things I’ve always wanted to do inside and outside of work. I am merely describing my experience of what the first 4 years of being a professional software developer feels like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Time Warp is going to happen, so you may as well set your life up in such a way that you’ll be proud of what you’ve done with it. If you come home after work and watch Netflix and scroll through InstaFaceTubeChat every night until you go to bed, your life will look different than someone who goes to the gym after work, or participates in an art, craft, or other hobby that builds some sort of skill over time. Generally, Mastery of a skill is more satisfying than doing a more idle activity like binge watching TV.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Side note: I’ll admit even watching movies and TV shows can be a “skill developing” hobby if you treat the film like a text and closely “read” it, like one of my favorite youtube channels/podcasts does: Wisecrack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you do some “Thing” that is structured and social that you find satisfaction in outside of work, and you can find “work-life balance” on a daily basis. You won’t feel like you need a long vacation (but you should still take one!) to feel refreshed and re-energized. This Thing can also be called a “Third Place”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is important to note that this Thing is not a romantic relationship! You may or may not find one in the process, but that isn’t the goal. You will need this Thing to be a permanent, unshakeable part of your life; something you can always do and lean on whenever life gets hard for a period of time. I’m not saying that you can’t get personal fulfillment or support out of a relationship — you definitely can! What I am saying is that it would be an unfair expectation to put on an person to give you personal fulfillment, socializing, and relief from stress 100% of the time. You have to be able to manufacture your own personal fulfillment. As my freshman year college roommate once wisely stated, “You have to live with yourself for the rest of your life. You may as well learn to be your own best friend.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“But Mike!”, you say, “My passion and personal fulfillment come from Software Development / Programming / My Profession! Can’t I just do more side projects to get more personal satisfaction?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sure, if that is really what you want. Think through your decisions carefully and what they mean in 10, 20, 50 years — when the Time Warp really kicks in. If you decide you are full steam ahead on being the “Best Software Developer” / “Next Zuckerberg, Jobs, Gates, and Woz Combined”, consider the opportunity cost of spending all of your time honing one craft. There’s health, social, and personal development opportunities that you are sacrificing by doing more of the thing that you already spend ~8 hours a day doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is generally good financial investment advice to “diversify”. This means your retirement account is not completely wiped out in the case of any one particular investment significantly loses value. Same with your life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What happens when you spend so much time and energy on your job, and then one day, your manager calls you into a meeting and tells you that the company needs to lay people off, and you’re one of them? (Haven’t experienced this yet, but a definite possibility!) If the entirety of your personal identity is wrapped up in your career, then you will be absolutely crushed. If you spent the other 50% of your waking life doing something else besides work/coding/hustling and getting personal satisfaction out of that, you won’t be nearly as crushed. You’ll still be worried about getting a paycheck, but you’ll be in much better shape mentally to get up, dust off, and find a new job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is especially true when you have been using your time outside of work to socialize with others who are likely employed at different companies than you are. As corny and self-help-y as it sounds, “your net-work is your net-worth”. In this case, using the financial analogy again, you are “diversified” in that you have actual friendships with people who would stick their neck out for you and put in a good word for you at their place of work. I am not advocating for being a sociopath and go to “networking” events every week just to get numbers in your phone. What I do suggest is that by making the Thing that you do a social activity where you are actually friends with those people, you are killing two birds with one stone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TL;DR: Have a consistent Thing that you do outside of work that adds balance to your daily life. A Thing that can grow into something that you can be proud of 5, 10, 20 years from now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enjoy your time in college, if you are there. If not, enjoy your time where you are at, but with a purpose. Embrace the Time Warp!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 06 Jan 2019 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>https://michaellady.github.io//dev/2019/01/06/Get-Ready-To-Time-Warp.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://michaellady.github.io//dev/2019/01/06/Get-Ready-To-Time-Warp.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>dev</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>On Being a &quot;Support Hero&quot;</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I enjoy having conversations with my &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/ladyistheman/&quot;&gt;brother&lt;/a&gt; about two of his main passions in life: basketball and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/League_of_Legends&quot;&gt;League of Legends&lt;/a&gt;. I love seeing him light up when he explains the latest League of Legends news or breaks down a basketball play. He has incredible domain expertise since he has played at a relative high level in each. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=E6fijiuQDx0&quot;&gt;He started&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#1&quot;&gt;(1)&lt;/a&gt; on the varsity basketball team in High School in both his junior and senior years, and at his peak, he achieved Diamond I ranking (0.06% of players hold this rank at any one time) in League of Legends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I noticed one day that both of these games are 5v5 team games, each with their own “meta-game” or simply “meta”. The meta for a game is a set of generally held beliefs or principles about how people “should” &lt;a href=&quot;#2&quot;&gt;(2)&lt;/a&gt; play the game that on average produces the most desirable outcome. These principles coalesce into 5 specialized player “roles” in both basketball and League of Legends. Each role balances the others out, all working together to win the game. The particulars aren’t important right now, so to keep it simple let’s just call one player role a “Support Hero/Champion” or “Support”, and the others are “Carry Hero/Champion” or “Carry” roles. The terms “Support Hero/Champion” and “Carry Hero” are borrowed from Real Time Strategy games like previously mentioned League of Legends or DOTA where a player controls a single avatar, typically called a “Hero” or a “Champion” that can cast spells and attack enemies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-meta&quot;&gt;THE META&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Carry players are the ones “carrying the team” and “putting the team on their back” &lt;a href=&quot;#3&quot;&gt;(3)&lt;/a&gt;. These players make the big plays that the layperson can appreciate. Their names are well-known because they are the ones taking shots and scoring; something that very visibly turns the tide of the game. In order for these Carry players to have the opportunity to be big stars by taking shots, someone else needs to NOT take shots: the Support player.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Support player is in a constant battle to ESTABLISH and MAINTAIN the necessary conditions/environment for the Carry player to thrive. If for example, the Support player(s) in basketball are having a hard time getting the ball across half court (due to a full court press, etc), this does not allow for the Carry player to set up and move into a good scoring position. It doesn’t matter how good the Carry player is at scoring if they never have an opportunity to touch the ball.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, the Support player is no slouch in their individual contributions to the team either. They can hold their own with their individual skills, because that is ultimately how each person operates and contributes to a team: as individuals. In addition to maintaining an environment where the Carry is free to exert and maximize their scoring skills, the Support players also try to find ways to make the Carry better, more effective, and effectively MULTIPLY their success. That’s how I see Support players: FORCE MULTIPLIERS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like multiplication, maybe because I’m a nerd who played too much Warcraft III and enjoyed using units that made others more effective with spells or passive “auras”. Let’s say for example if a Support player joins a basketball team, and they’re able to add just 10% armor poi-I mean, more points on the board (~10 points in an average NBA game) through just their presence on the court alone, without scoring themselves. They could do this by passing and cutting to the rim 10% more effectively than the average player so that the Carry players have better opportunities to score. That’s the difference between winning and losing MANY close games according to the average &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.teamrankings.com/nba/stat/average-scoring-margin&quot;&gt;NBA margin of victory&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;an-invisible-thread&quot;&gt;AN INVISIBLE THREAD&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have only recently identified this invisible thread that has been pervasive throughout my life: my affinity towards being a Support player. I’m choosing to acknowledge it and embrace it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started my Support player career in youth baseball. I was always in the outfield. The coaches claimed it was because I was bigger, so I had a better arm to throw from the outfield. Looking back on it, it was also because I wasn’t as quick or as coordinated with catching ground balls as the smaller kids who got to play in the action-packed, quick twitch infield &lt;a href=&quot;#4&quot;&gt;(4)&lt;/a&gt;. I believe this began my mental distinction between me and the “skilled” players in whatever sport I played.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A similar story played out in my youth basketball days, where my main job was being a “space eater” by making it harder for the other kids to drive to the basket. I think I scored maybe a dozen points in my entire organized basketball career.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ever since I started playing organized football (6th grade - flag football) I always played Center on the Offensive Line. The Center is the person who “snaps”/“hikes” the football to the Quarterback (the most important Carry player on the team) to start every play. Probably the most thankless position on the Offensive Line &lt;a href=&quot;#5&quot;&gt;(5)&lt;/a&gt;. I only got recognition when I screwed up and snapped the ball over the Quarterback’s head, or there was a fumble on the “under center” exchange &lt;a href=&quot;#6&quot;&gt;(6)&lt;/a&gt;. But I was a leader. I didn’t verbally lead much. I didn’t get up in front and yell encouraging, motivating things. I was very unconfident and insecure with myself at the time, but I knew that at least I could lead by example by working as hard as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please don’t take my recounting of my non-starring roles on sports teams as me complaining about my lack of success in sports due to me being slow and uncoordinated. I feel quite the opposite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel very grateful to be born into a great, loving, supportive, upper-middle class family and have a great set of talents to work with to earn starting spots as a Support player &lt;a href=&quot;#7&quot;&gt;(7)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am grateful for the time I spent playing team sports and the lessons I learned by playing the roles that my coaches guided me towards &lt;a href=&quot;#8&quot;&gt;(8)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With that frame of reference in mind, speaking out of gratitude, I’m going to illustrate how I’ve seen this Carry/Support dynamic plays out in the professional world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-workplace-meta&quot;&gt;THE WORKPLACE META&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have seen a similar meta of Support and Carry players that applies to the workplace. I am on the “build engineering” / “continuous integration” team. This team of Support Heroes is responsible for orchestrating the process of running the right combination and sequence of software on the right hardware at the right time. We establish and maintain an environment where our Carry players (developers) can test their code before they merge it with everyone else’s code so we have a high level of confidence that their changes don’t cause any major bugs in our app.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To use a different sports analogy, the developers are like the “skill players” on an NFL team. We have a star quarterback (a software architect), who directs where the receivers and running backs (feature developers) should run to catch the ball and score points for the team. Scoring points in this context is developers creating new features that makes customers want to buy the product. If the offensive line (build engineering) allows defenders to disrupt the play in the backfield and the quarterback gets sacked or the running back gets tackled for a loss (bugs in the automated build and test system), we no longer have an environment where our skill players can score points and win the game. I’m embracing the challenge of playing on the offensive line again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is solely the lineman’s responsibility for protecting the quarterback and skill players from defenders. If a defender gets through and sacks the quarterback, it is on the linemen alone. But when a score is achieved by the skill players, it is solely the skill players involved in a play that get credited with the yards gained and touchdowns scored in their personal stat line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most people “follow the ball” when watching sports. That’s where the most interesting action is: anticipating the opportunity to celebrate a score. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nfl.com/videos/san-francisco-49ers/0ap2000000146412/8-The-Catch&quot;&gt;The drama of a quarterback scrambling to avoid defenders to then precisely deliver a pass to a spot where only his receiver get grab it is exciting!&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=JyVfrwwEwgA&quot;&gt;Or the thrill of the running back evading and escaping defenders on his way to the end zone.&lt;/a&gt; The skill players who run with the ball are the obvious choice for who the camera zooms in on when they score and celebrate a touchdown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What the camera often overlooks is the offensive linemen who were left behind in the play &lt;a href=&quot;#9&quot;&gt;(9)&lt;/a&gt; who established and maintained the conditions for the quarterback to deliver the perfect pass, or for the running back to make a cut to daylight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to call out and celebrate the efforts of “linemen” of the world, the Support Heroes. They are the workplace’s unsung heroes and need their time in the sun because they as a unit tend to shy away from the spotlight and just want to do their job to the best of their ability without complaint for the good of the team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-dark-side&quot;&gt;THE DARK SIDE&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a dark side to being a “Support Hero”. By virtue of the position, they do not get a lot of credit. They are susceptible to take on more than what is required of themselves without complaint because that is what they believe is going to make the team successful. To the point where they break.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What really caused me to notice and analyze this “Support Hero” pattern throughout my life was when my brother described a situation where he was taking on way too much work and feeling overwhelmed without letting anyone know. I knew exactly what he was talking about because I had experienced same situation not too long ago. It isn’t in his nor my nature to openly boast about our accomplishments nor complain about our workload, we just focus on the task at hand and get it done, no matter how long it takes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While this is “noble”, it isn’t &lt;em&gt;adaptive&lt;/em&gt; or even &lt;em&gt;productive&lt;/em&gt; in a corporate environment where there is “always more work to do”. If we do not let others know how much work we are doing, we will continue to take more on. The ironic thing is that when we take too much on, our overall progress and productivity slows to a crawl due to trying to juggle so many responsibilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;metagame-planning&quot;&gt;METAGAME PLANNING&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Support Heroes more often than not need someone to tell them when to &lt;em&gt;stop&lt;/em&gt; working. They need help to define and focus on the most important priorities, and then delegate the tasks that don’t require their specialty out. The most important priority to me is not necessarily the most important priority to my manager, so frequent one on ones (at least once a week) “meeting of the minds” time is crucial to get on and stay on the same page. This is where I have come to realize the importance and value of a good manager.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Managers are much like coaches in the NFL. They need to define the overall strategy translate it to tactics executed by their players. They need to define what is and is not a player’s role on the team so they can work most effectively to contribute the most value to the team and ultimately, to the customer. &lt;a href=&quot;#10&quot;&gt;(10)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;force-multiplier&quot;&gt;FORCE MULTIPLIER&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Support Heroes are a force multiplier in a team environment (which is effectively ALL environments where other people are involved). Support Heroes are the stone that sharpens Abraham Lincoln’s axe when he says, “Give me six hours to chop down a tree and I will spend the first four sharpening the axe”. The axe is the Carry Hero who does the thing that accomplishes the goal, but they can be even more effective with a Support Hero to help sharpen them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Support Heroes are reliable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Support Heroes will never let the team down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Support Heroes make everyone else better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Support Heroes don’t score the points, but they help win the game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;Footnotes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;1&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
(1) If you watch the first three plays on my brother’s personal HIGHLIGHT video, they are ASSISTS. By his count, he has about the same number of personal makes vs. assists. These are THE FUNDAMENTALS being played at a high level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
(2) I have an issue with “should” because at first glance, I feel like it’s limiting creativity. But I realize that “creativity loves constraint”, so players can get creative within the meta itself. The meta is simply a framework or a common language that everyone understands to build off so that 5 complete strangers can play together in a cohesive manner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;3&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
(3) Like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=1P0yfq2wDvU&quot;&gt;Greg Jennings&lt;/a&gt;. Or &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=gd_Vd43Vxa0&quot;&gt;Marshawn Lynch&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;4&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
(4) I was alright at baseball. I hit two home runs, but it was pretty boring most of the time in the outfield.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;5&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
(5) I haven’t seen a major motion picture about a Center, yet. I’m looking at you, Michael Oher. But, interestingly enough, the OL as a position on average, gets &lt;a href=&quot;http://work.chron.com/position-nfl-gets-paid-least-12427.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;paid&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; in the NFL, third to only Pass Rushers and Quarterbacks. The cited article has an interesting explanation for those three positions in particular.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;6&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
(6) Probably the strangely socially-acceptable aspect of the sport. I played the position for 7 years. Looking back at it if I were to try to explain to an basically anyone outside of the US, it would be awkward to say the least.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;7&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
(7) I was one of the strongest guys on the high school football team and I ran a 6:10 mile in middle school track. Point is, I wasn’t a “late bloomer”, I was lucky to have some physical gifts that gave me an advantage early on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;8&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
(8) I did try out for running back freshman year of high school football. That lasted two days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;9&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
(9) There are occasions when &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=JyVfrwwEwgA&quot;&gt;linemen deliver superhuman performances and are able to run ahead of ball carrier (who, by the way, is supposed to be the fastest guy on the field) downfield to deliver critical blocks&lt;/a&gt;, but that’s generally the exception, and not the average case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;10&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
(10) I’ll probably expand on this more in a future post where I dive deep into one of the most effectively run organizations on the face of the planet: The New England Patriots, even though I’m an Atlanta Falcons fan.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 21 Nov 2017 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>https://michaellady.github.io//dev/2017/11/21/On-Being-A-Support-Hero.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://michaellady.github.io//dev/2017/11/21/On-Being-A-Support-Hero.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>dev</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Importance of Mentorship</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Hey all,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I mentioned an injury last time, but that will NOT be the main focus of this post! I will need meniscus surgery to make my right knee 100% better. I’ll be getting it in December.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the meantime, I’m doing what I can and working around it. I’m following the advice of one of my main mentors, Brian Riskas of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/rmdsystems/&quot;&gt;RMD Systems&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;dont-be-an-idiot-and-rush-back-to-training-until-it-is-taken-care-of-ask-me-how-i-know&quot;&gt;“Don’t be an idiot and rush back to training until it is taken care of. Ask me how I know.”&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blunt, personally-experienced lessons like these take a certain kind of relationship to be communicated effectively. I’ve heard his hands crackle like a “cement mixer” when he grips a Gi, and I am not keen on having my knee possess those same properties, so I take what he says seriously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is one of many times when he’s given me a nugget of wisdom free of charge (well, maybe at the cost of a beer or two 😉). I try to treat talking with Brian as if he were me 10 years from now in an alternate dimension where I was a mechanical engineer and I was sending a message back though a spacetime machine. I’m not saying I agree with 100% of what he says, but let’s just say I put more weight in it than the average “13 Simple Hacks to Change Your Life” listicle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a perfect example of why I want to write in this format. Not knocking Brian’s advice nor delivery, but he and I had a well-understood friendship prior to him giving me his blunt wisdom. You, the reader, and I don’t really have that kind of relationship, at least not yet. This longer format helps develop an understanding for communicating important ideas that they don’t teach you in school.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;inflammation&quot;&gt;Inflammation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I started this post off with something inflammatory such as, “Don’t be an idiot”, and you didn’t know me, you would likely not be open to anything else I had to say and you would immediately browse to your next tab out of the 37 you already have open. You wouldn’t give me a chance to explain how I came to know a particular fact where if I, like Brian, had to personally experience it. I could say something about our current political discourse here, but I won’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s essentially how “mentorship”, heck, any productive conversation, dare I say, “communication” between two humans works. It takes the work of two people: one with an intention of sending a message through spacetime and the other open to receiving messages (that may or may not be from another dimension). If one doesn’t want to send, nor if the other wants to receive, it doesn’t work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;duh&quot;&gt;“Duh”&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may be thinking, “yeah, well duh, Mike, of course that’s how it works”. I’m sorry, but sometimes it’s helpful to spell things out really plainly to see a different perspective. See &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.codinghorror.com/rubber-duck-problem-solving/&quot;&gt;Rubber Ducky Programming&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There have been many times in my life where I wasn’t open to receiving messages (knowingly and unknowingly), but messages were being sent to me, and vice versa. I was (and still am sometimes) not aware enough to believe that there were messages actually being sent to me. Other times, I send the “correct” or “accurate” message content, but I delivered it in a way that rubbed the person the wrong way, even if it was truthful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key, as Jocko says, is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=q5SHjSnynzw&quot;&gt;“Mind Control”&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#one&quot;&gt;(1)&lt;/a&gt;. TL;DR: Be more aware of and in control of your thoughts, because they are what make up “you”. How well you control your own thoughts dictates how well you are able to control other people’s thoughts. Uh oh, sounds like Jocko is up to no good, is he?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He says the better you can “detach” yourself from your ego and “get out of your own head” to see the other person’s perspective, the better you can mold the verbalization of your thoughts to achieve the desired outcome of the communication with that person. This helps your thought get transferred in such a way that the other person has the best chance of interpreting that thought as precisely as you understood it when you sent it. Now it is up to the receiving party to take that message, or leave it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;message-received&quot;&gt;Message Received&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I highly recommend everyone to try to find a willing &lt;a href=&quot;#two&quot;&gt;(2)&lt;/a&gt; in-person mentor who is someone you look up to and hope to achieve something similar one day, and find a way to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.garyvaynerchuk.com/giving-without-expectation/&quot;&gt;provide them value&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As corporate as that sounds, “providing value” could be as simple as treating the person to a coffee, a Jiu-jitsu roll, etc. If this is not possible (make sure you tried the providing value part), reading long form articles and books from people that you want to be like work here as well, but not as effective or as personalized &lt;a href=&quot;#three&quot;&gt;(3)&lt;/a&gt;. You’ll pick up on soon (if not already) the kind of person I strive to be like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Un)fortunately, we live in a society where we don’t have structured apprenticeships where there is a designated “master” and “apprentice”. Because of this, you have to get your mentoring/support from multiple sources. If you are the average of the five people you interact with the most, choose those five “positions” carefully. As carefully as if you’re forming an All-Star basketball team that has to beat the Warriors at home. Yes, that carefully. I will expand on this in another post, but it is very important to spend most of your time with people who have the same goal / same path through life as you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to Brian for the advice that prompted this post. Check out his &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=pF0YMF9W2hU&amp;amp;list=PLk4CDwBkUfpI1ExKUUUscP0N8vR3ywzpP&quot;&gt;crazy spider robot&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.rmd-systems.com/drone-services/&quot;&gt;drones&lt;/a&gt; that he builds!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;one&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
(1) If you couldn’t tell already, I love referencing things. This is going to be a normal thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;two&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
(2) You can’t just “demand” someone be your mentor. They have to be motivated to see you succeed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;three&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
(3) &lt;a href=&quot;https://news.ycombinator.com/&quot;&gt;Hacker News&lt;/a&gt; keeps me up to date with the zeitgeist of the tech world, with many insightful linked articles and comments from other professionals in the industry. This might need its own post.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 19 Oct 2017 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://michaellady.github.io//dev/2017/10/19/The-Importance-of-Mentorship.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://michaellady.github.io//dev/2017/10/19/The-Importance-of-Mentorship.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>dev</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The MOST Important Resource</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-your-most-important-non-renewable-resource&quot;&gt;What is your MOST important, non-renewable resource?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t use caps lock that often, but when I do, it means I’m passionate about it. This resource is used in both business and personal life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Technology? You can always buy more of it and optimize its use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Money? You can always make/beg/borrow/steal more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Health? Getting warmer, but not quite, at least not directly &lt;a href=&quot;#one&quot;&gt;(1)&lt;/a&gt;. This deserves its own post, but barring inherited predispositions towards disease and injury, you have more control over your personal health than nearly anything else in your life. You have direct control over your own &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/joerogan/status/580797582223511552&quot;&gt;“meat vehicle”&lt;/a&gt;; you don’t have to ask permission from a bureaucracy to change what food you put in your mouth or how much physical activity you perform. Use that to your advantage &lt;a href=&quot;#two&quot;&gt;(2)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;time&quot;&gt;Time&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Time once spent, cannot ever be gotten back. AND you only have a limited, finite amount of it &lt;a href=&quot;#three&quot;&gt;(3)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those seconds that turn into minutes, that turn into hours, that turn in to days/months/years cannot be returned, reused, or repurposed for personal fulfillment or enjoyment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take a hard look about how many times you open up Facebook or other social media and “news” sites in a day. There always seems to be “dead time” to check it. I’m just as guilty, if not more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My job involves waiting for code to compile and for automated tests to run, so there is plenty of opportunity for “dead time” in between my day’s tasks. That’s when the phone comes out and the brain turns off as I mindlessly scroll from one headline, “Stephen A. Smith ‘disappointed’ in Cam Newton” to another “Iranian Hackers Targeted Deloitte Via A Seriously Convincing Facebook Fake”. (The irony is not lost on me that you’re probably reading this from me posting on Facebook.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m able to mitigate the mindless scrolling with the &lt;a href=&quot;https://freedom.to&quot;&gt;Freedom app/web blocker&lt;/a&gt; (not an affiliate link). It works pretty well, and has a technically interesting blocking mechanism, but I still want to analyze the motivation for why we want to turn out brains off and let the phone do the thinking for us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;cliche-alert&quot;&gt;Cliche Alert&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s cliche at this point, but we have a fear of missing out. We’re always waiting for something to happen. We want to be one of the first people to know something “new” and then repost it to show our friends how much we know about the world. (Again, the irony is not lost on me that I’m posting this as if I know something about the world, but I will give myself the credit of actually writing this whole post, not just reposting what someone else said.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But when has reading something from Facebook/Reddit/Hacker News/Social Media fundamentally changed your life? How many times have you made a life decision based on a single source of posted media or content? For me, zero, and I would hazard a guess that it is zero or close to it for you as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we’re not changing our lives around based on the “7 Easy Little Ways You Can Greatly Improve Your Health”, (even though it says something important about health!), then what are we getting out of bite-sized articles? (Side note: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bustle.com/articles/134854-8-tips-for-writing-a-listicle-that-will-get-published&quot;&gt;my favorite meta-listicle&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think of personal media consumption (and learning / life experience in general) as like a constant, flowing stream of water. This stream carves out paths in the unshaped bedrock of your mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each headline digs into the bedrock a bit while still going along a pre-existing path to reinforce an idea. The overall bedrock is molded by this stream. Learning is in the direction of this flowing stream.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;where-is-your-stream-flowing&quot;&gt;Where is your stream flowing?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I challenge you to evaluate the content you choose to view on a daily basis and the thoughts that arise from that content. Is it supportive of who you want to be? Is it carefully chosen to carve out the direction you want your mind to go?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t get me wrong, I’m not advocating for your life to be 100% “productive” (whatever that means) and 0% fun. There has to be a yin and a yang, an ebb and flow (topic for a future post). Go ahead and watch that cat video, share those dank memes, catch up on celebrity gossip. Just don’t do it “mind-less”-ly out of habitx. Be “mind-full” of the stream you are shaping your bedrock with and how often you are doing so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to change the direction of your stream, you are my motivation for creating this content. I want to be a part of the stream that positively shapes people’s minds and help them find life in the “dead time” that may not have been positive and supportive otherwise. Plus, I have gotten a lot out of writing this by crystallizing my thoughts and expressing myself more eloquently than I am normally able to in a conversation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Look out for more posts from me in the future about heady topics such as: Grit, Humility, Mentorship, Injury, as well as lighter topics like the music I listen to, what I do for fun, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you for reading!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Footnotes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;one&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
(1) The total amount and quality of time one has is heavily influenced by the aforementioned “Health” factor, so invest your time in a “guaranteed ROI” by improving your fitness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;two&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
(2) I constantly need to remind myself about this. Luckily, I enjoy physical activity. Unluckily, I don’t enjoy green things, and love carbs. Find ways to make incremental, consistently-held changes in your life. This will be a post at some point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;three&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
(3) Probably the most shocking and awkward to explain phone background I’ve had for about 4 months is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.garyvaynerchuk.com/youre-gonna-die/&quot;&gt;“You’re Gonna Die” from Gary Vaynerchuk&lt;/a&gt;. Currently it is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=IdTMDpizis8&quot;&gt;“Good” by Jocko Willink&lt;/a&gt; since I’ve gotten injured. More on that later.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 12 Oct 2017 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://michaellady.github.io//dev/2017/10/12/The-Most-Important-Resource.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://michaellady.github.io//dev/2017/10/12/The-Most-Important-Resource.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>dev</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
